Guide to the Time Inc. Books Group 1963-1988, 2015 MS 3009-RG 28
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Books Group Records
1963-1988, 2015
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 28
27.75 Linear feet in 29 record cartons and 1 flat box
The Book Division formed out of the Life Book Division in 1961 and was later renamed Time-Life Books. While Time-Life Books was Time Inc.'s main imprint and book publishing department, Time Inc. owned several other book publishing, subscription, or direct marketing ventures and companies including Little, Brown and Company and the Book-of-the-Month Club prompting the creation of an executive oversight group. The Books Group Records include office files from the group vice president documenting major changes and decisions for all departments, offices, and subsidiaries within the Books Groups; records from the Books and Arts Associates; samples of series from Time-Life Records, later renamed Time-Life Music; files on the Iran Publishing Project; and files from the Time-Life Travel Club.
Arrangement
Organized into five series:
Series I. Group Vice President Files
Series II. Books and Arts Associates Records
Series III. Time-Life Records / Time-Life Music Series
Series IV. Iran Publishing Project Files
Series V. Time-Life Travel Club Records
Historical Note
Books were published by the various magazines prior to the formation of the Books division. According to The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980, Life's book projects were the most successful, and the Life books division is what became the separate Book Division in 1961.
The Book Division formed with Jerome Hardy as publisher and Norman Ross as editor. Time Inc. announced this new division in a January 9, 1961 press release stating it already had fourteen books projects underway. The group is called the Book Division until Time Inc. names it Time-Life Books in the 1963 corporate annual report. There was never an official announcement of the name change. The group was still referred to as the books division (in lowercase) interchangeably with Time-Life Books.
In 1968 an executive oversight group called "Books, Arts and Recordings" was created led by vice presidents Rhett Austell and Charles Bear. According to an August 1968 staff memorandum, the group's primary function was to coordinate the activities of the Book Division with the related activities of the book publishing subsidiaries Little, Brown and Company and New York Graphic Society; and to work with executives from partially-owned subsidiary General Learning Corporation and the foreign publishers in which Time Inc. owned minority interests.
The 1969 annual report has the first mention of the Books and Arts Associates (BAA), a new advisory management group for book publishing foreign investments. Austell is now the executive vice president overseeing Books, Broadcast, Films, Records, and the BAA. The BAA also briefly oversaw the domestic publishing subsidiaries Little, Brown and Company and the New York Graphic Society. By 1975 BAA's oversight diminished, and its responsibilities were slowly taken over by the Books Group executive office.
In 1989 a new unit called Books Direct formed and included Time-Life Books and the subsidiary Book-of-the-Month Club. A press release announcing this new unit describes Time-Life Books as the "Largest direct marketer of continuity book, music and video products." In 1990 Time-Life Books was renamed Time Life Inc.
According to the 1974 annual report, Time-Life Books primarily published book series on broad topics and marketed them by direct mail. It occasionally published single-subject volumes. Internationally Time-Life books were printed in 26 languages.
DEPARTMENTS AND SUBSIDIARIES
While Time-Life Books was Time Inc.'s main publishing unit, the Books Group oversaw several other book publishing, subscription, or direct marketing ventures and companies acquired by Time Inc. The major subsidiaries were the textbook publisher Silver Burdett, acquired in 1962; the Boston-based publishing house Little, Brown and Company acquired in 1968; and the Book-of-the-Month Club officially acquired in 1977 although it worked with Time-Life Books prior to that. In November 1965, Time Inc. and General Electric (GE) create the General Learning Corporation (GLC) consisting of Silver Burdett and capital from GE. Scott Foresman and Company purchased GLC in July 1974.
Other ventures and subsidiaries include:
Time-Life Libraries (originally called The Span of Time) which formed in July 1965 to handle door-to-door sales of Time-Life books. It was also briefly known as the Time-Life Book Program. It took over telephone sales from Time Telemarketing in 1975.
Time-Life Audio, a department formed in 1970 to "produce information and entertainment on audio cassettes for the home" as a subscription service. The first program is "The Executive Voice," produced with the editors of Fortune featuring interviews with business executives about their products and services featured in the news.
Time-Life Records, a subscription service for music series, later known as Time-Life Music.
Seven Arts and Book Find Club, which were book clubs purchased together in 1969 and merged. The name changed to Time Inc. Book Clubs in 1971, and the company dissolved in 1975.
New York Graphic Society (NYGS), publisher of fine art reproductions founded in 1925 by artist Anton Schutz and acquired by Time Inc. in 1966. NYGS owned Alva Museum Replicas and later Museum Collections, Inc. Both were companies that produced art object replicas for retail sale. Little, Brown took over operations of NYGS in 1974. Time Inc. sold NYGS in 1981.
Haverhill, direct marketing firm of high-price gift items, owned by Time Inc. from 1971 to 1975.
Oxmoor House was the direct marketing books subsidiary of Southern Progress Corporation, a company acquired by Time Inc. in 1985.
Citations:
"Heinrich Schutz, 79, Art Dealer and Editor." New York Times, February 23, 2002.
Time Inc. Annual Reports, MS 3009-RG 31, New-York Historical Society.
Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
Time Inc. Subject Files, MS 3009-RG 1, New-York Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials may include contracts, personnel files, and correspondence with personally identifying information. Restricted materials are located in box R64. Unreformatted audiovisual material and digital material in the collection is not accessible. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library. Additional records about the history of the Books Group and its subsidiaries can be found in the Time Inc. Subject Files (MS 3009-RG 1) and the Time Inc. Reference Files (MS 3009-RG 3). The Time Inc. Video Group Records (MS 3009-RG 41) may also have materials related to books collaborated on by the two groups.
Scope and Contents
The Books Group Records include office files from the executive level the group vice president documenting oversight of and major changes and decisions for all departments, offices, and subsidiaries within the Books Groups; newsletters and financial records from the Books and Arts Associates, the group created to monitor investments in foreign publishing companies; samples of the series sent out by the music subscription service Time-Life Records, later renamed Time-Life Music; files on the special project undertaken by Time Inc. to assist in the set up of a educational publisher in Iran; and files from the short-lived club offering travel services.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Book clubs (Bookselling)--United States; Corporation records.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Music publishing; Organization files.; Publishers and publishing -- Iran; Publishers and publishing -- Management; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Travel clubs; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.; Austell, Rhett; Brack, Reginald K., Jr.; Manley, Joan D.
- Series I. Group Vice President Files, 1963-1988; 14.5 Linear feet in 16 record cartons
  Biographical Note
  Rhett Austell joined Time Inc. in 1950 and held prior roles at Time in circulation and as general manager. He was Time-Life Books (TLB) publisher from 1964 to 1969, as well as being named a corporate vice president in 1966 and serving on the boards of General Learning Corporation and New York Graphic Society. In 1968 he and vice president Charles Bear served as co-chairmen for the new executive oversight group "Books, Arts and Recordings." In 1970 Austell became executive vice president over TLB, Time-Life Broadcast, Time-Life Films, Time-Life Records, and Books and Arts Associates. By 1974 he was a group vice president (GVP), and departments added to his oversight included Home Box Office (HBO) and Sterling Manhattan Cable Television. By 1978 when Joan Manley takes over as GVP, the groups for Books and Video are separate.
  Joan Manley joined TLB at its formation in 1960 and served as the TLB circulation director, then director of sales before being named the TLB publisher in 1970. She was the first woman to hold the role of publisher at Time Inc, and in 1971 became the first woman corporate vice president of Time Inc. By 1978 Manley took over as the Books Group GVP. Along with serving as GVP, she also was chairman and chief executive officer of Time-Life Books, Inc., the incorporated entity overseeing TLB and served on the board of Book-of-the-Month Club, Inc. In 1981, John McSweeney, formerly the general manager of TLB, took over as chairman with Carl Jaeger as president, but Manley returned as chairman in 1982. A memorandum from her regarding the 1982 Books Group reorganization states she would no longer be CEO of TLB, but would transition back to only GVP with Reginald Brack taking over in the president and CEO role. Manley retired in August 1984.
  Reginald Brack joined Time Inc. in 1962. In the 1982 reorganization of the Books Group, he moved from his position as publisher at Discover to exchange jobs with TLB president Jaeger. Following Manley's retirement in August 1984, Brack became Books GVP along with taking over Manley's other former roles as chairman of Time-Life Books, Inc. and vice chairman of Book-of-the-Month Club, Inc. Brack was named chief executive officer (CEO) of the magazine group in December 1986.
  Citations:
  Prendergast, Curtis, and Geoffrey Colvin. 1986. The World of Time Inc.: The Intimate History of a Changing Enterprise, 1960-1980. New York: Atheneum. United States. 1977.
  Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
  Time Inc. Subject Files, MS 3009-RG 1, New-York Historical Society.
  Scope and Contents
  The Administrative Files contain records from the holders of this position, primarily Joan Manley and Reginald Brack with earlier files from Rhett Austell. There are also records from administrative assistant Joan Berk acting on behalf of Manley and Brack. Materials were not separated by office holder, but look to be kept together by the administrative staff.
  Records include administrative files documenting decisions at the executive level and the oversight of all Time-Life Books staff and projects; files on Time Inc.'s investments in foreign publishing companies; and files on companies other than Time-Life Books within the Books Group.
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Administrative Files
  Subseries I.B. International Files
  Subseries I.C. Subsidiary Files
  - Subseries I.A. Administrative Files, 1963-1986 (bulk 1972-1986); 4 Linear feet in 5 record cartons
    The Administrative Files document decisions at the executive level and the oversight of all Time-Life Books staff and projects. Records include interoffice correspondence with staff in the various offices within the Books Group, lists of staff for the various offices and subsidiaries, staffing change announcements, and organization charts for the Books Group and Book-of-the-Month Club. Items of interest include discussion about whether to merge TLB department Time-Life Audio into Time-Life Records, a photograph of the TLB staff working on the Iran Publishing Project, and publisher Joan Manley's 1973 memorandum to GVP Rhett Austell arguing against the proposal to remove "Life" from all company names after the closure of Life magazine.
    Organized alphabetically.
    - Access (Computer newsletter), 1983-1984 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 1-2)
    - Acquisitions: Queries, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 3)
    - Acquisitions: Possible, 1972-1980 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 4-5)
    - Affirmative Action, 1985 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 6)
    - Anniversary: 25th, 1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 7)
    - Announcements, 1971-1985 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 8-12)
    - Artandi, George, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 13)
    - Austell, Rhett, 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 14)
    - Bair, Steve, 1985 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 15)
    - Banana Republic (Melvin Ziegler), 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 16)
    - The Best of Life, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 17)
    - Board of Directors: Executive Committee, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 18-19)
    - Bonus Forms, 1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 20)
    - Books Group Boards, 1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 21)
    - Book Catalog (Gift catalog), 1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 22)
    - Brack, Reginald to Joan Manley, 1982-1984 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 23-24)
    - Budget, 1981-1986 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 25-27)
    - Capital Appropriations, 1982 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 28)
    - Cavendish, Marshall (Peter Godfrey), 1973-1974 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 29)
    - Cavendish, Marshall (Peter Godfrey) [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R64)
    - College Textbook Publishing, 1984 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 30)
    - Conference: Lyford Cay, 1985 (Offsite-box 3428, Folder 31)
    - Conflict of Interest Letters, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 1)
    - Constable, George, 1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 2)
    - Copyrights, 1972-1979 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 3)
    - Corporate Development (New products), 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 4)
    - Corporate Policy Committee, 1986 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 5)
    - Creative Advisory Board, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 6)
    - Definitions of Terms, undated (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 7)
    - Dell Publishing, 1975 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 8)
    - DeVries, Wes, 1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 9)
    - Dinner: Lantos, Tom, 1986 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 10)
    - Director Mail/Marking Association, 1975-1983 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 11)
    - Dushkin Publishing Group Ltd, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 12)
    - D: Miscellaneous, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 13)
    - Edit, 1971-1984 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 14-15)
    - Edit/Publishing, 1976-1982 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 16)
    - Education, 1979 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 17)
    - Educational Testing Service, 1972 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 18)
    - ELHI Textbook Adoption, 1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 19)
    - Encyclopedia: Hardy, J. Memorandum, 1963 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 20)
    - Fawcett World Library, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 21)
    - Financial Miscellaneous, 1971-1977 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 22)
    - Franklin Book Programs, 1973-1977 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 23)
    - Fulfillment, 1986 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 24)
    - Gallagher, Ralph, 1974 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 25)
    - G: Miscellaneous, 1984 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 26)
    - Harris, Charles: Howard University Press, 1975-1980 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 27)
    - Henry, Bill, 1983-1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 28)
    - House Ads and Inserts, 1972 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 29)
    - H: Miscellaneous, 1981-1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 30)
    - Ideas and Suggestions for Books, 1970-1986 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 31-34)
    - Information Services, 1984-1985 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 35-36)
    - Insurance, 1981 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 37)
    - Investment Reduction, 1982 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 38)
    - Iran, 1979-1984 (Offsite-box 3429, Folder 39)
    - Italcambio (Mints), 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 1)
    - I: Miscellaneous, 1984 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 2)
    - J: Miscellaneous, 1975-1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 3-4)
    - Kehoe, Michael: Books Suggestion, 1979 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 5)
    - K: Miscellaneous, 1980-1984 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 6)
    - Library of America, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 7)
    - Linen, Christopher, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 8)
    - Linen, James A., 1977-1979 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 9)
    - Lines of Responsibility, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 10)
    - List Analysis, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 11)
    - List Rentals, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 12)
    - Look (Cowles), 1971-1973 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 13)
    - L: Miscellaneous, 1980-1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 14)
    - Management Development, 1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 15)
    - Management Inventory Books Group [RESTRICTED], 1981 (Offsite-box R64)
    - Management Meeting, 1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 16)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 17)
    - Master List Proposal, 1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 18)
    - Matimore, J. Clarke, 1972-1975 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 19)
    - McClelland, Jack: The Vintage Years, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 20)
    - McKinsey and Company, 1983 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 21)
    - McKinsey Books Group Project, 1984 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 22)
    - McSweeney, Jack, 1971-1983 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 23-24)
    - Medallic Art Company, 1971 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 25)
    - Memorandum to Korn and McSweeney, 1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 26)
    - Millenium, 1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 28-34)
    - Miscellaneous [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R64)
    - Model, 1983? (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 35)
    - Morgan and Morgan, 1975 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 36)
    - Move to Alexandria, 1976 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 37)
    - Munro, Dick Memorandum on Books and Information, 1987? (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 38)
    - Mydans, Carl and Shelley: U.S. Occupation fo Japan, 1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 39)
    - New Business Development, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 40)
    - N: Miscellaneous, 1980-1983 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 41)
    - OPL (Other Publishers' Libraries?), 1974 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 42)
      A memorandum states that Time-Life Books' (TLB) sales of other publishers' books are called OPL in "computerese." This file also discusses the TLB logo.
    - Paperbound Editions, 1975-1980 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 43)
    - Pello, Joanne, 1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 44)
    - Personnel, 1976-1986 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 45-47)
    - Photography as Art, 1975-1976 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 48)
    - Photography Year, 1972 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 49)
    - Picture Policy (Reproduction Rights), 1973-1979 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 50)
    - Planet Earth, 1982 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 51)
    - Pofcher, Monroe, 1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 52)
    - Postal Service and Costs, 1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 53)
    - Pricing, 1971, 1981 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 54)
    - Privacy, 1974-1976 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 55)
    - Production, 1973-1984 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 56-57)
    - P: Miscellaneous, 1982-1985 (Offsite-box 3430, Folder 58)
    - Quality of Life Fund (Wilderness), 1972 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 1)
    - Reorganization, 1982 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 2)
    - Reorganization [RESTRICTED] (Offsite-box R64)
    - Restructuring, 1983 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 3)
    - Rights and Permissions: Photographs, 1973 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 4)
    - Series: Understanding Computers, 1984 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 5)
    - Series: Your Home, 1985 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 6)
    - Seven Arts, 1974 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 7)
    - Shepley, James, 1975-1978 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 8)
    - Special Sales, 1971-1975 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 9)
    - Steering Committee, 1984-1986 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 10)
    - Stewart, Paul: Memoranda, 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 11)
    - Stone, Martin, 1981-1986 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 12)
    - Strategic Planning and Five-Year Plans, 1975-1985 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 13-21)
    - S: Miscellaneous, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 22)
    - Telephone Sales, 1979 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 23)
    - Time-Life Audio, 1970-1973 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 24)
    - Time-Life Films, 1975-1979 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 25)
    - Time-Life Libraries, 1971-1974 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 26)
    - Time-Life Records, 1972-1973 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 27)
    - Time-Life Software, 1981-1984 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 28-29)
    - Time-Life Video, 1986 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 30)
    - T: Miscellaneous, 1973 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 31)
    - Video Books, 1984 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 32)
    - Videocassettes, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 33)
    - Video Education and Training Task Force (Bob Ellis), 1979 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 34)
    - "Working Smarter", 1981 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 35)
    - W: Miscellaneous, 1974 (Offsite-box 3431, Folder 36)
  - Subseries I.B. International Files, 1968-1988; 4.5 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
    The International Files document the executive oversight of Time Inc.'s minority investments in foreign publishers and include reports from the managing director of the Books and Arts Associates (sometimes called Book Arts and Associates), the advisory management consulting team originally responsible for direct communications with the foreign companies before the GVP's office took over. Records document the strategic plans for the international investments and book projects undertaken in collaboration with international publishers.
    Organized with general international files at the front, followed by files on the international investments monitoring group Books and Arts Associates, then alphabetically by region. Regions are defined by the original order.
    - General, 1971-1981 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 1-3)
    - Administration, 1982-1983 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 4)
    - Board Memorandum on Japan and Mexico, 1984 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 5)
    - Board Memorandum on Minority Investments Abroad, 1972 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 6)
    - Fulfillment, 1972-1981 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 7-8)
    - International Production and Distribution (IPD), 1971-1976 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 9)
    - Legal, 1972-1979 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 10)
    - Management Information System, 1971 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 11)
    - Operations Committee, 1971-1972 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 12)
    - Strategic Plan: Europe and SOPAC, 1982-1988 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 13)
    - Translation Costs, 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 14)
    - XTIs (Cross Throw In), 1979-1980 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 15)
    - Books and Arts and Associates: General, 1972-1981 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 16-18)
    - Books and Arts and Associates: Alexander Project, 1978-1982 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 19-20)
    - Books and Arts and Associates: International Investment Strategy, 1974 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 21)
    - Books and Arts and Associates: Morfogen, Zachary, 1977-1982 (Offsite-box 3432, Folder 22)